<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [
	<!ENTITY rfc2629 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml'>
]>
<rfc docName="R-Type RFC" category="info">
	<front>
		<title>R-Type Network Game Protocol</title>
		<author initials="S.N." surname="Ninon" fullname="Simon Ninon">
			<organization abbrev="Epitech">Epitech</organization>
		</author>
		<date month="November" year="2014"></date>
		<area>Game Network Protocol</area>
		<workgroup>Tasser Team</workgroup>
		<keyword>R-Type</keyword>
		<keyword>RFC</keyword>
		<abstract>
			<t>This memo presents the Network Game Protocol used for the R-Type.</t>
		</abstract>
		<note title="Conventions Used in This Document">
			<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in [RFC2119].</t>
		</note>
	</front>

	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction">
			<t>This document provides a full documentation for the Network Game Protocol of the R-Type Game.</t>
			<t>It provides all the necessary information to understand how to communicate with a R-Type server and with a R-Type client: commands, protocols, packets format...</t>
			<t>It also explains when to use the TCP and the UDP network protocols when you are communicating with a R-Type client or with a R-Type server.</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Transfert Description">
			<t>The R-Type Network Communication Protocol is based on the TCP and UDP network protocols.</t>
			<t>The R-Type Network Communication is a binary protocol.</t>
			<section title="TCP">
				<t>The TCP protocol is used for all the commands that are not related to a game action.</t>
				<t>Basically, all the commands that are related to the client's menu (list games, create game, delete game, ...) must be sent by using the TCP network protocol.</t>
				<t>This protocol has been chosen to provide a safe client-server communication for important commands</t>
			</section>
			<section title="UDP">
				<t>The UDP protocol is used for all the commands that are related to a game action.</t>
				<t>Basically, all movements informations are transmitted by using the UDP network protocol.</t>
				<t>This protocol has been chosen to provide a fast and efficient client-server communication</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="Data Unit Dormat">
			<t>Each command is formatted by using the following diagram: a common header and a specific body.</t>
			<t>This configuration must be implemented by both TCP and UDP communication.</t>
			<figure>
				<artwork>
|-------------------------|
| HEADER |      BODY      |
|-------------------------|
				</artwork>
			</figure>
			<section title="Header">
				<t>The header is composed of a magic_code and of an instruction code.</t>
				<figure>
					<artwork>
|-------------------------------|
| magic_code | instruction_code |
|   int32_t  |      int32_t     |
|-------------------------------|
					</artwork>
				</figure>
				<t>The magic_code must have a value of 0x150407CA. If it doesn't, the packet must be considered as invalid and the connection must be closed.</t>
				<t>The instruction_code corresponds to a specific value depending of the command. It must be used to know what is the size of the packet's body.</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Body">
				<t>The packet's body contains a c-structure data which depends of the command that has been sent.</t>
				<t>Each command has its own structure with a different size and different fields.</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="TCP Commands">
			<section title="handshake">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x0A</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command must be sent just after beeing connecting to the R-Type server.</t>
					<t>It informs the server that you are a valid R-Type client.</t>
					<t>Until you send this command, the other commands you'll send may not be treated by the server.</t>
					<t>This command does not have a body.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command must be sent just after accepting a R-Type client.</t>
					<t>It informs the client that you are a valid R-Type server.</t>
					<t>Until you send this command, the other commands you'll send may not be treated by the client.</t>
					<t>This command does not have a body.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="createGame">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x01</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command is used to create a new game on the server.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|-------------------------------------------------|
|   name   | levelName | nbPlayers | nbSpectators |
| char[64] |  char[64] |   char    |     char     |
|-------------------------------------------------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The name attribute is the name you want to give to the created game.</t>
					<t>The levelName attribute is the name of the level script you want to use.</t>
					<t>The nbPlayers attribute is the maximum number of players who can play to the created game. This number must be between 1 and 4.</t>
					<t>The nbSpectators attribute is the maximum number of spectators who can attend to the created game. This number must be between 1 and 4.</t>
					<t>The server must answer with an error command packet.</t>
					<t>In case of success, the client becomes the owner of the game and can delete it.</t>
					<t>The ownership can not be given to an other client.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command has no equivalent server-side.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="joinGame">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x02</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command is used to join a game as an active player.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|----------|
|   name   |
| char[64] |
|----------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The name attribute is the name of the game you want to join.</t>
					<t>The server must answer with an error command.</t>
					<t>In case of success, the client joins the game and the server must send informations concerning players positions, bullets positions, current script execution time...</t>
					<t>In case of success, the client can send UDP packets which stand for client actions (eg: move, fire).</t>
					<t>In case of success, the server must notify the already connected players that a new client has joined.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command has no equivalent server-side.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="observeGame">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x0E</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command is used to join a game as an observer.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|----------|
|   name   |
| char[64] |
|----------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The name attribute is the name of the game you want to join.</t>
					<t>The server must answer with an error command.</t>
					<t>In case of success, the client joins the game and the server must send informations concerning players positions, bullets positions, current script execution time...</t>
					<t>In case of success, the client can not send UDP packets which stand for client actions (eg: move, fire).</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command has no equivalent server-side.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="showGame">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x03</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command is used to ask for game informations.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|----------|
|   name   |
| char[64] |
|----------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The name attribute is the name of the game which you want information.</t>
					<t>The server must answer with an error command.</t>
					<t>In case of success, the server must send a showGame command.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command is used to send game information to a client.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|----------------------------------------------------------------|
|   name |levelName|nbPlayers|maxPlayers|nbObservers|maxObservers|
|char[64]| char[64]|   char  |   char   |    char   |    char    |
|----------------------------------------------------------------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The name attribute is the name of the game concerned by the information.</t>
					<t>The levelName attribute is the name of the level script used in the game.</t>
					<t>The nbPlayers attribute is the number of clients that are currently playing on the game.</t>
					<t>The maxPlayers attribute is the maximum number of clients that can play on this game.</t>
					<t>The nbObservers attribute is the number of clients that are currently observing the game.</t>
					<t>The maxObservers attribute is the maximum number of clients that can observe the game.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="leaveGame">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x0F</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command is used to leave a game.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|----------|
|   name   |
| char[64] |
|----------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The name attribute is the name of the game you want to leave.</t>
					<t>The server must answer with an error command.</t>
					<t>In case of success, the client leaves the game.</t>
					<t>In case of success, the client can not send UDP packets which stand for game actions any more.</t>
					<t>In case of success, the server must not send UDP packets which stand for game actions any more.</t>
					<t>In case of success, the server must notify the other players that a client has left.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command has no equivalent server-side.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="deleteGame">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x04</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command is used to delete a game.</t>
					<t>This command can only succeed if you are the owner of the game.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|----------|
|   name   |
| char[64] |
|----------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The name attribute is the name of the game you want to delete.</t>
					<t>The server must answer with an error command.</t>
					<t>In case of success, the game is deleted.</t>
					<t>In case of success, all the players and observers must be forced to leave the game and must be notified by the server.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command has no equivalent server-side.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="listGames">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x05</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command is used to list all the games.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of an empty body.</t>
					<t>The server may answer with a loop of showGame commands.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command has no equivalent server-side.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="listLevels">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x10</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command is used to list all the levels.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of an empty body.</t>
					<t>The server may answer with a loop of showLevel commands.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command has no equivalent server-side.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="updatePseudo">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x06</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command is used to update the client's pseudo.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|----------|
|  pseudo  |
| char[64] |
|----------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The pseudo attribute is the pseudo you want to use.</t>
					<t>The server must answer with an error command.</t>
					<t>In case of success, the pseudo is updated.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command has no equivalent server-side.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="disconnect">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x07</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command is used to close the connection with the server.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of an empty body.</t>
					<t>The server must handle the disconnection and close the connection.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command has no equivalent server-side.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="error">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x00</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command has no equivalent client-side.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command is used to notify a client if an error occured during the last received command treatment.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|-----------------------------|
| instructionCode | errorCode |
|     int32_t     |  int32_t  |
|-----------------------------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The instructionCode attribute is the code of the instruction concerned by the error packet.</t>
					<t>The errorCode attribute is an error code corresponding to the state of the instruction excecution.</t>
					<t>The errorCode must have one of the following values:</t>
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>OK: 0x00</t>
							<t>KO: 0x01</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="endGame">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x0B</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command has no equivalent client-side.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command is used to notify a client that the game has ended.</t>
					<t>This command may be sent in different context: the game has been deleted, the player has been killed or the game has ended.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|----------|
|   game   |
| char[64] |
|----------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The game attribute is name of the concerned game.</t>
					<t>After sending this command, the server must not send UDP packets which stand for game actions anymore.</t>
					<t>After receiving this command, the client can not send UDP packets which stand for game actions anymore.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="showLevel">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x11</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command has no equivalent client-side.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command is used to send level script information to a client.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|-------------------------------------|
| levelName | scriptSize |   script   |
|  char[64] |   int32_t  | char[4096] |
|-------------------------------------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The levelName attribute is the name of the level script.</t>
					<t>The scriptSize attribute is the size, in bytes, of the script contained by the script attribute.</t>
					<t>The script attribute contains the level script data.</t>
					<t>The server must send a showLevel command for all the available levels to a new client.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="UDP Commands">
			<section title="move">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x08</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command is used to notify the server that the player want to move in the given direction.</t>
					<t>This command is composed  of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|-----------|
| direction |
|    char   |
|-----------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The direction attribute is direction the player want to take. It must be one of the following value:</t>
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>LEFT: 0x00</t>
							<t>RIGHT: 0x01</t>
							<t>TOP: 0x02</t>
							<t>BOTTOM: 0x03</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command has no equivalent server-side.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="fire">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x09</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command is used to notify the server that the player want to fire a bullet.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of an empty body.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command has no equivalent server-side.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="moveResource">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x0C</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command has no equivalent client-side.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command is used to notify a client that a resource has moved.</t>
					<t>This command is composed  of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|----------------------------------------|
|    id   | type |   x   |   y   | angle |
| int32_t | char | float | float | short |
|----------------------------------------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The id attribute is the id of the element. Each element has a unique id.</t>
					<t>The type attribute is the type of the resource. The type must have one of the following value:</t>
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>PLAYER: 0x00</t>
							<t>BULLER: 0x01</t>
							<t>ENNEMY: 0x02</t>
							<t>BONUS: 0x03</t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>The x and y attributes give the new position of the resource on the map.</t>
					<t>The angle attribute correspond to the direction of the resource.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="destroyResource">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x0D</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command has no equivalent client-side.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command is used to notify a client that a resource has been destroyed.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|----------------|
|    id   | type |
| int32_t | char |
|----------------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The id attribute is the unique id of the destroyed resource.</t>
					<t>The type is the type of the destroyed resource. It must have one of the following values:</t>
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>PLAYER: 0x00</t>
							<t>BULLER: 0x01</t>
							<t>ENNEMY: 0x02</t>
							<t>BONUS: 0x03</t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>Once the resource has been destroyed, its unique id may be reused for a newly created resource.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="updateScore">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x12</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command has no equivalent client-side.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command is used to notify a client about the score of a player.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|------------------------------|
|    id   |  pseudo  |  score  |
| int32_t | char[64] | int32_t |
|------------------------------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The id attribute is the id of the concerned player.</t>
					<t>The pseudo attribute is the pseudo of the concerned player.</t>
					<t>The score attribute is the score of the concerned player.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section title="timeElapsedPing">
				<t>Instruction code: 0x13</t>
				<section title="From Client">
					<t>This command has no equivalent client-side.</t>
				</section>
				<section title="From Server">
					<t>This command is used to notify a client about the current execution time of the script.</t>
					<t>This command is composed of the following body:</t>
					<figure>
						<artwork>
|-------------|
| timeElapsed |
|   int64_t   |
|-------------|
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>The timeElapsed attribute is the time elapsed since the beginning of the game.</t>
					<t>Even if the client must implement its own game loop, this command must be used by the client to adjust its intern game timer.</t>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="Annex">
			<section title="Instruction Code">
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>error: 0x00</t>
							<t>createGame: 0x01</t>
							<t>joinGame: 0x02</t>
							<t>showGame: 0x03</t>
							<t>deleteGame: 0x04</t>
							<t>listGames: 0x05</t>
							<t>updatePseudo: 0x06</t>
							<t>disconnect: 0x07</t>
							<t>move: 0x08</t>
							<t>fire: 0x09</t>
							<t>handshake: 0x0A</t>
							<t>endGame: 0x0B</t>
							<t>moveResource: 0x0C</t>
							<t>destroyResource: 0x0D</t>
							<t>observeGame: 0x0E</t>
							<t>leaveGame: 0x0F</t>
							<t>listLevels: 0x10</t>
							<t>showLevel: 0x11</t>
							<t>updateScore: 0x12</t>
							<t>pingTimeElapsed: 0x13</t>
						</list>
					</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Error Code">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>OK: 0x00</t>
						<t>KO: 0x01</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="enum Direction">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>LEFT: 0x00</t>
						<t>RIGHT: 0x01</t>
						<t>TOP: 0x02</t>
						<t>BOTTOM: 0x03</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="enum ResourceType">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>PLAYER: 0x00</t>
						<t>BULLER: 0x01</t>
						<t>ENNEMY: 0x02</t>
						<t>BONUS: 0x03</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
	</middle>

	<back>
		<references>&rfc2629;</references>
  </back>
</rfc>
